<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>BatMass: mass spectrometry data visualization on BatMass</title>
    <link>http://batmass.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content in BatMass: mass spectrometry data visualization on BatMass</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="http://batmass.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting started</title>
      <link>http://batmass.org/getting-started/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://batmass.org/getting-started/</guid>
      <description>This guide will quickly step you through the installation, creation of a project and viewing mzML/mzXML files.
Installation Download the latest release for your platform from GitHub.
  Windows installer
 It is preferable to install BatMass to non-system locations (e.g. not into Program Files or similar locations) as you might need Administrator privileges to modify the configuration file.    Linux installer
  MacOS installer
  Platform independent zip</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data access library: MSFTBX - Mass-Spec File Toolbox</title>
      <link>http://batmass.org/data-access-lib/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://batmass.org/data-access-lib/</guid>
      <description>The data access library is at the core of BatMass, but is a separate standalone project. It can be used in regular Java programs (read as a jar library) and NetBeans platform applications via the included NetBeans Module wrapper.
Features  Single API to mzML and mzXML files mzML and mzXML parsing  Very fast multi-threaded parser Can separately parse LC/MS run information, the index and data Separation of parsing of scan meta-information and spectral data Automatic indexing of the data  maps from scan numbers to scans maps from retention time to scans same maps separately at each MS level automatic DIA (data Independent Acquisition) detection and automated grouping of DIA MS2 scans according to the corresponding isolation windows   Memory management  can parse the whole structure of the run (all scans with all meta-info) and dynamically parse spectral data from the disk only when it&#39;s accessed an object can be used as the &amp;lsquo;owner&amp;rsquo; of loaded data, if the &amp;lsquo;owner&amp;rsquo; is garbage collected, and no other &amp;lsquo;owners&amp;rsquo; claimed the scans, the corresponding resources can be automatically released   Tolerance to broken index  automatically detects errors in the index, such as all scan offsets are the same (which happens with some versions of ProteoWizard&#39;s msconvert when converting large files) if the index is not present, will reindex the file   Tolerance to MS2 scan tags being enclosed in the corresponding MS1 scan tag (old data converted with ReAdW)   PepXML parsing/writing ProtXML parsing/writing MzIdentML parsing/writing  Usage Take a look at this tutorial for a short introduction and check the sources at github.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact information</title>
      <link>http://batmass.org/contacts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://batmass.org/contacts/</guid>
      <description>Please use the bug tracker to request additional functionality or report bugs.
Citing / Referencing the work If you use BatMass for your research or work, please cite the following paper:
Avtonomov D.M. et al: J. Proteome Res. June 16, 2016. DOI: 10.1021/acs.jproteome.6b00021.
The author and maintainer of the project Dmitry Avtonomov, Ph.D. (University of Michigan, Ann Arbor)
Email: dmitriya@umich.edu
http://dmtavt.com
General inquiries Alexey Nesvizhskii, Ph.D. (University of Michigan, Ann Arbor)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data access library (LC/MS files and simple Peptide ID examples)</title>
      <link>http://batmass.org/tutorial/data-access-layer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://batmass.org/tutorial/data-access-layer/</guid>
      <description>The data access library provides a relatively rich API to mzML/mzXML files (MS level, polarity, precursor isolation window, instrument data, etc.) and a few other file formats common to the proteomics field, such as PepXML, ProtXML and MzIdentML. In this tutorial will step through parsing some data, using the library as a jar in a simple console window application.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parsing pep.xml files</title>
      <link>http://batmass.org/tutorial/parsing-pep-ids/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://batmass.org/tutorial/parsing-pep-ids/</guid>
      <description>The data access library provides parsers for file formats common to the proteomics field, such as PepXML, ProtXML and MzIdentML. In this tutorial I&#39;ll show you how to parse a PepXML file.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overlay peptide IDs on 2D map</title>
      <link>http://batmass.org/tutorial/overlay-peptide-ids-on-map2d/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://batmass.org/tutorial/overlay-peptide-ids-on-map2d/</guid>
      <description>Overlaying contents of pepxml files on a 2D map.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Display custom data on 2D map</title>
      <link>http://batmass.org/tutorial/custom-drawing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://batmass.org/tutorial/custom-drawing/</guid>
      <description>How to display your custom data on Map2D without any coding. You&#39;ll need to provide a simple file format.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up development environment</title>
      <link>http://batmass.org/tutorial/setting-up-development-environment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://batmass.org/tutorial/setting-up-development-environment/</guid>
      <description>This guide will quickly step you through setting up the environment for developing new functionality for BatMass. All the downloads, setting up the IDE and up to building BatMass from scratch.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developing the first plugin</title>
      <link>http://batmass.org/tutorial/developing-first-plugin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://batmass.org/tutorial/developing-first-plugin/</guid>
      <description>We will step through developing one complete plugin, which will add support for a new type of files holding LC/MS feature information, which will be viewable as a table and can be overlaid on top of Map 2D view.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>License</title>
      <link>http://batmass.org/license/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://batmass.org/license/</guid>
      <description>Copyright 2016 Dmitry Avtonomov
Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the &amp;ldquo;License&amp;rdquo;); you may not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at
http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the License is distributed on an &amp;ldquo;AS IS&amp;rdquo; BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific language governing permissions and limitations under the License.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>